Feng Ye

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Victoria 3800 Finnerty Road, Victoria, BC V8P 5C2, Canada Tel: +1 (672) 995-7334 (mobile)

Email: yefengleaf97@gmail.com (preferred); fengye@uvic.ca

PRINCIPAL INTERESTS

My research interests span several areas in cyber-physical systems and distributed control systems, with a focus on distributed control and optimization, federated learning, smart grid, security and privacy preservation, attack detection, and their applications on microgrid and Internet of Vehicles.

APPOINTMENTS

Post-Doctoral Fellow

Sept. 2024 - Present

University of Victoria, Victoria, BC, Canada

 Research in privacy preserving and security of federated learning, platooning control of Internet of Vehicles under direction of Prof. Lin Cai.

ACADEMIC BACKGROUND

Visiting Ph.D. Student, Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Victoria, Victoria, BC, Canada

Oct. 2022 - Oct. 2023

• Research in privacy preserving and security of federated learning under direction of Prof. Lin Cai.

Ph.D., Control Science and Engineering

Sept. 2019 - Jun. 2024

Southeast University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China

- Ph.D. research in privacy preserving and security of control systems under direction of Prof. Xianghui Cao and Prof. Mo-Yuen Chow.
- Dissertation title: Research on Privacy-Preserving Method for Distributed Economic Dispatch in Microgrids.

 $\boldsymbol{B.S.},\;$ Electrical Engineering and Automation

Sept. 2015 - Jun. 2019

Northeastern University, Shenyang, Liaoning, China

SPECIAL ACHIEVEMENTS

Selected Awards

- People's Choice Award, Workshop on Future Ubiquitous Networks 2023-Spring, IEEE Victoria Section Joint VTS/ComSoc Chapter, Canada, May 2023
- Meritorious Winner Award, Mathematical Contest in Modeling, the Consortium for Mathematics and Its Applications, USA, Apr. 2018
- Honorable Mention Award, Mathematical Contest in Modeling, the Consortium for Mathematics and Its Applications, USA, Apr. 2017
- Outstanding Student Cadres Award, Northeastern University, Sept. 2017

Scholarships

- Ph.D. Candidate 83791 Qiuzhen Scholarship, Southeast University, China, 2024
- Ph.D. Candidate Scholarship, Southeast University, China, 2020 2023
- Postgraduate Student Scholarship, Southeast University, China, 2019
- National Encouragement Scholarship, Ministry of Education, China, 2017
- Undergraduate Student Scholarship, Northeastern University, China, 2016 2019

Invited Lectures

- A Random-Weighted Privacy-Preserving Distributed Algorithm for Energy Management in Microgrid with Energy Storage Devices, IESES 2020
- Simulating and Evaluating Privacy Issues in Distributed Microgrids: A Cyber-Physical Co-Simulation Platform, IECON 2021
- A Random-Weight Privacy-Preserving Algorithm With Error Compensation for Microgrid Distributed Energy Management, Workshop on Future Ubiquitous Networks 2023-Spring

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Byzantine-robust federated learning

Jan. 2023 - present

• Designed a Byzantine-robust federated learning algorithm to detect model poisoning attacks, which distinguishes malicious clients are based on probability distribution.

Secure control of distributed microgrids

Jan. 2021 - Dec. 2023

- Designed a collusion attack against distributed energy management systems based on the microgrid network topology, which undermines the economic utility of microgrids.
- Designed a novel false data injection attack detection method for distributed energy management systems based on the microgrid network topology, which can detect malicious devices in microgrids while preserve the data privacy of each device.

Privacy-preserving distributed coordinate control

Jan. 2020 - Jun. 2024

- Designed a novel privacy-preserving economic dispatch algorithm for distributed energy management system in microgrids, preserving privacy of the power information of devices.
- Drawed the upper bound of privacy-preserving performance of algorithms, and designed a multiplyingnoise-based general privacy-preserving average consensus framework.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• Guest Lecturer, University of Victoria ECE463/ECE514: Design and Analysis of Computer Networks 2024 - Present

• Guest Lecturer, Southeast University EE124: Large-Scale Grid Technology 2021

• Guest Lecturer, Southeast University SOA8122: System Identification and Modeling 2020

• Assistant and Lab Instructor, Southeast University SOA1180: Introduction to Communication Networks

2020 - 2023

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

- 1. F. Ye, X. Cao, M.-Y. Chow, and L. Cai, Privacy-Preserving Average Consensus: Fundamental Analysis and a Generic Framework Design, *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 70, no. 4, pp. 2870-2885, 2024.
- 2. F. Ye, X. Cao, Z. Cheng, and M.-Y. Chow, CASL: A Novel Collusion Attack against Distributed Energy Management Systems, *IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid*, vol. 14, no. 6, pp. 4717-4728, 2023.
- 3. F. Ye, Z. Cheng, X. Cao, and M.-Y. Chow, A Random-Weight Privacy-Preserving Algorithm With Error Compensation for Microgrid Distributed Energy Management, *IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security*, vol. 16, pp. 4352-4362, 2021.

- 4. **F. Ye**, X. Cao, L. Cai, and M.-Y. Chow, False Noise Attack Detection for Differentially-Private Distributed Control of Microgrids, Submitted to *Automatica* as a Regular Paper, under the 2nd round of peer review.
- 5. **F. Ye**, L. Cai, and X. Cao, Normal is Normal: A Novel Byzantine-Robust Federated Learning Algorithm against Model Poisoning Attacks via Probability Distribution of Gradients, *under review*.
- 6. Z. Cheng, F. Ye, X. Cao, and M.-Y. Chow, A Homomorphic Encryption-Based Private Collaborative Distributed Energy Management System, *IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid*, vol. 12, no. 6, pp. 5233-5243, 2021.

Conference Proceedings

- F. Ye, Z. Cheng, X. Cao, and M.-Y. Chow, A Random-Weighted Privacy-Preserving Distributed Algorithm for Energy Management in Microgrid with Energy Storage Devices, 2020 2nd IEEE International Conference on Industrial Electronics for Sustainable Energy Systems (IESES), Cagliari, Italy, 2020, pp. 249-254.
- 2. N. Hang, F. Ye, Z. Cheng, X. Cao, and M.-Y. Chow, Simulating and Evaluating Privacy Issues in Distributed Microgrids: A Cyber-Physical Co-Simulation Platform, 47th Annual Conference of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society(IECON), Toronto, ON, Canada, 2021.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Professional Activities

- Member, IEEE, 2024 present
- Graduate Student Member, IEEE, 2020 2023

Peer Reviewer

- Automatica, 2022 present
- IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2022 present
- IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security, 2023 present
- IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics, 2023 present
- IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics, 2020 present
- IEEE Transactions on Control of Network Systems, 2020 present
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal, 2023 present
- IEEE Network Magazine, 2023 present
- IEEE/CAA Journal of Automatica Sinica, 2022 present